Guide to the Charles Morgan Coit Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Charles Morgan Coit papers
1861-1870
MS 1497
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
(2 boxes)
The papers consist of photocopies of letters written by Charles Morgan Coit to his mother, sister, and brother George during the Civil War. Also included are photocopies of letters written by George Coit to his mother and sister and a photocopy of a letter by Mary Coit.
Coit, Charles Morgan, 1838-1878
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Received from Charles A. Coit, 1989.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Charles Morgan Coit Papers consist of correspondence written by Charles Morgan Coit to his mother, brother, and sister. The letters span his military career as adjutant, captain, and brevet lieutenant colonel in the Eighth Connecticut Volunteer Infantry from the fall of 1861 to the spring of 1865.
The letters deal with the daily tribulations faced by Coit and his regiment and cover such topics as living accommodations and sanitary conditions in various camps, the price and availability of food and clothing, weather and travel conditions, social life, morale, discipline, and descriptions of the skirmishes.
The papers were the gift of Charles A. Coit in 1989.
Biographical / Historical
Charles Morgan Coit was born on March 29, 1838. He was secretary-treasurer of the Chelsea Savings Bank of Norwich, Connecticut when he was mustered into the army on October 5, 1861. A member of the Eighth Connecticut Volunteer Infantry, Coit served as adjutant, captain, and later brevet lieutenant colonel. He fought in the battles of Antietam, Fredericksburg, and Petersburg. Coit was wounded at Fair Oaks on October 29, 1864 and was mustered out of service on May 27, 1865. Coit married Mary Hillard and had two sons, Charles and Augustus. He died by drowning on July 3, 1878 off the New London, Connecticut coast while attempting to save the life of his younger son.
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Coit, Charles Morgan, 1838-1878
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1861 September 30 - December 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1862 January 1 - March 31 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1862 April 4 - June 29 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1862 July 1 - October 31 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1862 November 9 - December 30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1863 January 1 - April 26 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1863 May 2 - September 10 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1864 March 1 - June 24, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1864 July 3 - December 31 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1865 January - Feb, May [Jun] (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence of George Coit, 1863 March 6 - March 18 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence of Mary B. Coit, 1870 August 5 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Transcription of correspondence, 1861 September 30 - December 30 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Transcription of correspondence, 1862 January 1 - June 29 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Transcription of correspondence, 1862 July 1 - December 30 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Transcription of correspondence, 1863 January 1 - September 10 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Transcription of correspondence, 1864 March 1 - October 29 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Transcription of correspondence, 1865 January - Feb, May - [Jun] (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Transcription of correspondence of George Coit, 1863 March 6 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Biographical material of Charles Morgan Coit, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)